All right.
So, I
It's tradition to go over a little bit
of what we did yesterday.
We talked about uh
six different conditions that you would
want to get ready for your meditation
practice even before you sit down. So,
these are things you have to take care
of
uh before you start trying to meditate,
all right?
Mhm.
What were they? What was the first one?
Yeah, like a conducive place. The place
should be nice. That had how many
conditions?
Five. You want to go for those?
The d- d-
What was the first one?
Yeah, place where you can get
uh honestly gotten provisions, right?
Honestly gotten
meditation hut, honestly gotten
food, honestly gotten propane, etc.,
right? What's number two?
Yeah, a place where somebody cool has
meditated before if you can find one. In
this country
it's short on them.
You have to create them, okay? But in
Tibet, there were thousands of caves
and, you know, hermitages that have been
blessed for a thousand years by
different practitioners. I went to one
in Mongolia. I went to the caves in
Mongolia.
And they had a wonderful feeling to
them, you know? So,
yeah, that's number two. Number three?
A good location meaning the place
shouldn't be too hot or cold. Shouldn't
get sick by staying there, okay?
Uh number four?
Oh, and the place should be
environmentally sweet, right? Like the
They're taking care of the water, you're
taking care of the land.
The land is well It's It's not being
poisoned by toxins and the water's not
being destroyed and the the place should
be honored
by the practitioner who's going to take
the heart of living there, okay?
What's the next one?
Remember we had it?
Oh, yeah, good companions. And they uh
Buddha Gotama was encouraging especially
those who are beginning meditation
to meditate with like-minded
friends who are
hardcore, heavyweights, okay? Don't
Don't Don't stay with spiritual
lightweights when you're doing your
meditation, you know? Who are going to
get up every five minutes from
meditation and go make some tea or
something, you know? Stay with them.
So, be with people Meditate with people
who are intense.
And then your meditation will get
better. It's like yoga, you know? If you
want to get good at yoga, go to
you know, go get your mirror and kick
every day by some really good teacher
and then you'll improve. If you just
stay with what's comfortable for you,
uh then you won't improve, right? Okay.
Uh so, good companions, dedicated,
hardcore practitioners have companions.
Last one?
Get your stuff together, which meant uh
be you know, yeah.
Know what you're going to meditate
about, like have your
have some training
and then uh have the necessary If you
need a book to do the retreat, if you
need some materials, have them all
ready. If you need an empowerment, get
the empowerment.
Uh
concentrate on having
all the training that you need before
you meditate and before you start trying
to meditate.
Yes, it'd be like trying to do a
headstand
from the beginning without anyone to
help you, right? From the first day of
your yoga. And it It might even hurt
you.
So, it's better to be well trained
before you undertake especially a
retreat, right?
And I met a lot of people who, you know,
I'm always bragging about my three-year
retreat.
And then people say, "Well, I did a
retreat." And then I say, "Well, what
did you do?"
I didn't know. I did a weekend and we we
went out in the forest. And I I said,
"Well, what kind of practices did you
do?" And they said,
"Well, you know, we just hung out." You
know, and
So, the people who are going into
three-year retreat now, they've had
what, seven years of
training
uh before they go into three-year
retreat. So, you should have
good training before you try to meditate
because meditation,
you know, it's difficult and you need
good training.
So, that was the first of the six
conditions. Second?
Reduce your needs, okay? Like don't
Don't be
What do you say?
Don't demand a lot of nice stuff while
you're meditating, while you're
practicing. Don't Like let go of all
those things like I need a certain kind
of food or I need a certain kind of
place to stay or I need certain kind of
computer while I'm there, you know? Give
up on all those.
Just
reduce your level of need, right? Then
number three?
Yeah, whatever you get, be joyful and be
happy and be grateful. And we were
talking about how every material thing
you ever comes to you, it could be a
door on your new cabin. It could be uh
the lunch that came to you today.
It could be just the space that we're
having the teaching in. Like be grateful
for the things around you, right? People
have spent their lives
uh people have The people who built this
church, you you know they had They're
not rich people and they they worked
hard. They probably built it with their
own hands and and they really
worked hard and you should enjoy You
should like thank them while you're
sitting here.
And and someone gives you food or
someone feeds you, you get You paid for
a a dinner then
but be grateful for the people who
served it and be grateful for the people
who did the farming and the people who
brought it to you on a truck. And these
people I had one American person that
said, "Oh, but they get paid."
You know, I'm I'm like, "Yeah, but they
get paid, but how much do you pay a
person for an hour of human life?"
Which they cannot replace, which is
irreplaceable. You know, what do you
What? Five bucks? 10 bucks? 100 bucks?
You know, what's an hour of a person's
life really worth? And then thank them.
Thank them. Be Be grateful for things,
okay? Next.
Huh?
Yeah, don't be busy, okay? Don't get too
busy.
Busy is relative, right?
But anyway,
don't be busy to the extent that it
would that it would harm you med-
meditate,
right?
Thank you.
Sorry?
Oh, did we miss ethical?
Is that next?
Uh
The power
to meditate
comes from being nice to other people.
We I
You always take I like to take Dharma
Mittra's class, Shri Dharma Mittra's
class, when I go to New York, you know?
And then he does all these First he does
an hour of really hard asanas and then
he has this I don't know I still don't
know if it's a joke or not,
but he says, "Okay, now we'll start the
class."
You know, and you're already starting to
sweat and you're like panting and he's
like, "Now we'll start the class. That
is the warm-up."
And uh
then he kills you for another hour. And
then at the end he always makes you sit
down and he always says the same thing.
He says,
He says, "Be nice to other people, you
know?"
And then he says, "Okay, you can go
home."
But he makes you sit there for five
minutes and and hear the same talk and
it always ends with, you know, "Be nice
to other people." So, the power
behind meditation comes from just being
nice to other people and and other
creatures, right? Being kind to other
people. The the
the karma
to meditate well comes from taking care
of other people, okay? So, if you
if your mind feels distracted, you might
want to look into that, okay?
Cuz that's why your mind is distracted.
All right. What's number one?
I said number one.
Yeah, just
try to give up random thoughts of
wanting things and disturbing thoughts,
random thoughts.
The kind of thoughts you get if you talk
on the phone to somebody who's a little
kooky just before you go to bed.
And And then you try to sleep and you
can't sleep or your dreams are weird,
right? Or something like that. Like you
know, someone who disturbs your thoughts
or or like television shows or things
like things that disturb your thoughts.
Like give up those, okay?
So, those are preconditions for
meditation. If I had to rate them,
which do you think is the most
important?
Yeah,
an ethical way of life, okay?
Why? Because your mind The condition of
your mind is also a karmic result,
right?
I Obviously, whether you're
Obviously, whether you get money or not
or whether people yell at you or not,
this is all coming from karma, right?
Whether you get in a car accident or
not, this is coming from karma.
But your thoughts are also coming from
karma. The condition of your own mind is
also coming from karma.
How you treat other people. So, the
cheap way to meditate well is just be
nice to other people, you see? Then you
save all this trouble on your knees
and and you know, hours and hours of of
wasted battling with your mind, you see?
Cuz the battles you have to fight are
because you're not nice to people. So,
if you're nice to people, there won't be
any big battles to fight when you get
into meditation. People came to our
three-year retreat site afterwards and
they looked at the cabins the year and
they said, "Oh, it's so pastoral and
it's so peaceful." And I'm sure you had
just the most
you know,
what do you call warm and friendly
time in those cabins and I said,
it was like being in a
Every day Every day was bloody. Every
day was a war, you know?
Every day was a fight. You have no idea
what was It was silent and it was bloody
and
you know, it was hard. And uh
you won't have all the Those fights will
be fights that never happened if you
collect the right karma ahead of time.
Then you just sit down and suddenly
you're having I call it popcorn. Popcorn
means, you know, pop pop pop pop pop pop
pop pop and great things are happening
to you and wonderful thoughts are coming
to your mind. They don't come by
accident.
They come because you're nice to other
people. Every time you're nice to
someone,
you make karma to have a sweet
meditation. So, rather than having a
Vietnam war in the corner of your living
room where you meditate,
uh
concentrate on on being ethical and kind
to people, right? No killing, no
stealing, no sexual misconduct, no
lying, no slander, no harsh words, no
idle gossip, no craving, no ill will, no
envy. These are the 10 right here.
Okay. Avoid those things and then the
meditation will come, right? Beautiful.
Beautiful good meditation, okay? So, we
finished the preliminaries. We're on to
your reading book.
Uh
Neba. I forgot to tell you one one thing
yesterday. Why is it going to take 10
years to finish this course?
Uh this book is 800 pages, okay? We can
do three pages a session.
You You figure.
Uh
and uh
My idea is we're starting with the
meditation section at the end of the
volume two of this book. Then we'll by
Tuesday night we'll be on the emptiness
section from this book.
And uh
And And in this uh 10-day session, we
will complete uh the sections on
meditation and on on
on how reality really works. Again, the
reason to study how reality really works
is that
you can stop fighting reality and you
can just get the things you want uh
automatically, you know?
Uh I'll tell you a story tomorrow. I
can't tell you today.
Something's happening today
from karma and we just planted it. Uh
and it's very beautiful.
Yeah, I'll tell you tomorrow, okay? But
uh like
the reason to study these things is that
you can make good things happen in your
life and in the world, right? And we
were talking about going to
British Airways last What? Last week?
Two weeks ago?
And uh they have 43,000 workers and
and they asked us to come and help them
and teach them ways to
to make the workers happy and make more
money at the same time. Pay the workers
more and make more stock share at the
same time, which is not possible.
Right?
So, we're doing that and it's very
beautiful. So, the idea is that
you take these holy instructions and you
use them for something.
Cool.
Like
peace in the world or something like
that.
Okay?
So, what do then we go through the rest
of the book? That will take I don't
know.
X years.
And then um I had an idea. You see,
we're skipping to the end now, right?
We're doing the meditation section and
the
how does British Airways work section,
okay?
And then
if we go this way, then a couple years
from now when we finish, we won't have
any fun because the end of the book will
already be gone, you see? Which is what
we're doing now.
So, there's the mother the grandfather
book of this book is what?
The Lamrim Tsongkhapa. The great book on
the steps of the path by the teacher of
His Holiness the First Dalai Lama, just
a couple.
It was written 600 years ago.
Uh that book has about 400 pages on
emptiness
and meditation together.
Uh she loves them down.
And uh
I thought we could just like go over
there for a while
to get the end again. Got it?
So, that's why it's going to take 10
years. Okay, here we go.
Uh
Neba Neba She ne du tul mi.
Now I will teach you how to really reach
deep meditation. Once you've got all
those things ready, all you're all
ready. You didn't have to get a question
but you know that. Okay.
Utam There's a book called
Madhyantavibhanga.
It means uh
It was written 16 centuries ago
by the next Buddha in the world, okay?
Maitreya.
He was very close.
And uh
He He wrote a book about He He wrote how
to meditate. He has a system or a
technique how to meditate. 16 centuries
ago he granted this teaching, okay?
Uh
Mm.
So, here's what he said in his book.
The book means are separating the
extremes from the middle. What's that
mean?
I don't
Is it true that anything in your world
works? Does your car work?
Does your refrigerator work? Does this
book work? Yes, I think it does.
Nothing works.
Nothing.
Does it exist?
Does it function? Sure, I guess.
Yeah, so when somebody like me says
nothing works, your car doesn't work the
way Your car doesn't work the way you
thought it did.
Okay? Then the tendency is for people to
overdo it. They say Geshe Michael said
nothing at all works ever.
Okay? Did I say that?
No.
I just said nothing works.
Okay. Anyway, two extremes. Utam Nam Je
means avoid the two extremes, go to the
middle.
Something like an aspirin will work and
something like your car will work if you
have helped other people with headaches
and if you have driven people around in
the past. Okay? Right? Yoga will work
if you help the sick and the elderly.
Then you go to yoga class, it will help
your body. And if you don't, it will
hurt your body, okay? That's why there
are what?
Restorative classes.
Which are to help people who hurt
themselves in yoga. Okay.
Uh
Neba
Neba Nam Par He says there are five
Okay, this is going to be your life for
the next few years.
You're just about to hear it. Neba Nam
Par means Maitreya the coming Buddha
says there are five classical challenges
that will come up during meditation.
There are five classical challenges that
every meditator has to face.
And you have to learn them and then
then du je ge. There are eight
uh actions you can take to counter those
five challenges. Those five problems can
be countered through eight different
methods. And this is how people have
been meditating on this and other
planets for countless years, okay?
Uh this teaching is is very very
profound and very ancient. Much older
than this world, okay?
And uh
So, you have to learn it. There are five
problems, there are eight ways to stop
those problems, okay?
Uh
Ten gyu le chu wo.
If you rely on the eight antidotes,
you'll be able to maintain what?
Here are the Then he lists the five
problems, okay? Here we go. Le lo. Le lo
is about the only Tibetan word that
sounds like what it is in English.
Le lo.
What's le lo?
Laziness. Tradition Traditionally it
means laziness, but in meditation it has
a different meaning.
I don't feel like meditating today,
okay? I like to translate it as I don't
feel like it today. It's not really
Laziness is sort of like that, right?
Laziness is like you you you are you're
sitting around all day drinking Dos
Equis or Corona.
Uh
it's not like that.
Uh it means you get up and you look at
your question and you look at your clock
and you think about stuff you have to do
today and you think, you know, I just
don't feel like doing it today. That's
le lo. That's problem number one. If we
can't overcome problem number one, you
won't have the other four problems.
Okay?
All right.
Okay, make it better. Uh
le lo dam ni ba la ba la dam je. Ba la
dam je means
you forget the instructions. You forget
the instructions.
It has the special interpretation that
we'll talk about. Number three,
chin dam ga. Say chin dam ga. Chin dam
ga. These are your friends. You have
lived with these your whole life. Say
chin dam ga. Chin dam ga. These are the
two extremes of meditation.
A good meditator is driving like watch
my hands.
Watch a person's hands when they drive,
right?
Watch a person who's just learning to
drive.
You know, and they're always going off
the road. And then another driver, a
good driver, he's you know, everybody
else is they're talking on their phone
and they're they're not paying
attention, but their hands are going
like this constantly.
They are correcting. Good meditation
is a process of correcting constantly
between two
two dangers. You are you are not you're
trying to hit not hit that curve and you
are trying not to hit that curve. When
Rinpoche was teaching me this, I was
teaching him how to drive.
He was 60 years old. He had never ridden
a bicycle.
And all we had was a stick shift
Volkswagen.
So the day he was teaching me this, I'm
this took 2 years to teach him to drive.
And he he
we were going down the street near
Freehold, New Jersey.
And there was a guy out mowing his lawn
and there was a row of garbage cans.
And so Rinpoche jumped up on the curb,
nails all the garbage cans.
And then stops and opens the door. And
then the guy's doing all this stuff and
Rinpoche says, "What's that mean when
you say that you did that going
down the street?"
And I said, "Oh, he's just greeting you,
Rinpoche."
You know.
So I had to get out. But anyway, I've
never forgotten this teaching.
So there's garbage cans over there and
there's garbage cans over there and you
don't want to hit them, okay? What's
over here? Chinwa. Chinwa means I get
all funny around you anyway.
Chinwa means uh
dull. You get dull. You get sleepy, no
energy. You meditate, you get bored,
sleepy, dull. That's that's one extreme,
okay? The other extreme is called guppa.
Guppa means you get restless.
Or your mind gets stirred up, okay? And
meditation is riding
a middle path between us. And until you
reach the very heights of meditation
which I'll show you in a minute.
Okay, I need you to write that.
Okay, try.
So you're going to be correcting until
you get really good at meditation,
you're going to be constantly correcting
and trying not to hit the two garbage
two rows of garbage cans, okay? That's
the idea. Constant correction like this,
okay?
Between the mind goes too low and then
the mind gets too excited. When your
mind gets too excited, you're thinking
about lunch. When the mind goes too low,
you're like
you know, you you spaced out, okay?
Dull, okay? Got it?
We had a retreat one time in Connecticut
and we thought up this what do you call
it? Per- perfidious
approach.
That's not such a good word.
Uh
mean, it was mean of me.
we said we're going to have a meditation
retreat and then we gave them a big big
lunch and we made everybody eat a lot
and we kept them up late the night
before. We gave them like six or five
hours of sleep and then we fed them a
lot of heavy food and then we had a
meditation session.
Cuz we wanted them to see chinwa.
You know,
and they did.
Uh
and they never forgot it.
But I don't want to waste your time and
it's also expensive.
Okay.
Um
Okay, uh chinwa now.
Uh
Guppa. So chinwa guppa, that's problem
number three, right?
Hitting either garbage can in mind is
problem number three.
We're going to go through this chart
uh made by the the the editor of this
text which is one of the Dalai Lama's
teachers.
And um
we'll be going through this chart. But
what we're undertaking now, what we're
embarking on now, the five problems, the
eight antidotes, etc. is all summarized
in this beautiful chart, okay?
Uh so we translated it down here into
English and we have copies for
everybody. Uh we're still going to take
your money. I think the plan is to still
take your money, but someone has covered
the cost.
Say again?
Oh, they covered $5. Anyway,
more money is going for somebody's cabin
in this year's retreat than was going
yesterday.
Okay. And basically, if you don't have
any money and you want one, you can have
it for free, okay?
Uh
Yeah, I'll cover I'll cover that, okay?
Yeah.
Okay.
So anyway, on this chart are the five
problems and the eight antidotes and
you'll we'll talk about it, okay?
You got to have a chart like by the
break. You can have a chart or
something.
Okay, we'll do that at the break.
All right.
Uh okay, here we go.
Uh
Those are the five problems of
meditation.
Number two is number four.
Uh he's my teacher is saying you have to
use the eight antidotes to fix the five
classical problems of meditation, okay?
I just did four and five. Oh, I didn't
only do four and five. I'm sorry.
You're very clever. Okay.
Do Number four is du me je. Du me je
means failing to take action when you
should be. You're headed towards the
garbage cans and you don't turn back.
Okay?
Number five is du je.
Du je means taking action when you
should
leave leave it.
Your mind is going smooth. Your
meditation's going smooth. Don't mess
with what In my company they used to say
the factory manager used to say, "If it
ain't broken, don't fix it."
Okay? If you're not having a problem,
then
then don't like investigate how you're
doing cuz that'll take you towards the
garbage cans. Got it?
When you when you finally get to that
point where it's flowing, let it flow.
Those are the five classical problems.
Uh they're not number one and number
two.
So you can use the eight antidotes to
fix these five.
Uh ting nge zin dub pe me nang me
gyal cha
den sa de the uma gom rim so shung cha
mo nang so sum pa
le gwa ba me pe nang
So
ting nge zin dub pe me nang me
uh Pabongka Rinpoche is saying, "If you
want to learn how to meditate and you
want good instructions for learning how
to meditate, gyal cha turn to the great
books of Maitreya." How many?
All right, five great books of Maitreya.
Turn to the great books of Maitreya,
okay?
Or sa de
uh study the great books on the levels
of realization by Asanga, okay? Master
Asanga.
Who saw emptiness directly.
Um or uma gom rim by
Vimalakirti.
Master Vimalakirti.
So when Lama Christie started to teach
uh meditation at Diamond uh
we we spent a lot of time choosing the
text that she would use for six or seven
years.
And and those that was on the top of the
list, right? Vimalakirti. So these are
ancient meditation manuals.
Uh so shung cha mo nang so sum pa le gwa
ba me pe nang you can't find any better
instructions than those.
Rung cha ke me nang du tab sel ne
gom
gom bzhi gyur gyi people like you and
me. Say rung cha.
Uh
it's right there the first of them.
Rung cha rung cha
means
people like you and me. In English we
say people like you and me, right?
And
it's all through this text. This is the
most beautifully written book in Tibet.
Forget that the subject is the most
beautiful subject.
And forget that it's the best
teaching ever.
The writing is the most beautiful
writing ever done in Tibet. Really, it's
extraordinary, okay? You if you
the writing is is like Shakespeare, you
know? Beautiful, really really beautiful
and clean and perfect, you know?
Anyway,
Pabongka Rinpoche kept saying rung cha
which for a high lama is a
is a joke. He's saying he's saying like
you and me have these problems, you
know?
And he keeps saying you and people like
you and me, okay? But just to read that
word in Tibetan is very sweet. You know,
here's this
extraordinary master who never had this
problem for the last 18 lifetimes
and he's saying, "You know, guys like
you and me
we have always problems."
People like you and me, we can
all we need to do is just refer to one
of these great classics about
meditation.
And then we can learn to meditate. Den
pa me nang ba
shung cha mo nang so she chos su sum ne
but you see people who they encounter
one of these classics about meditation
and they think, "Oh, that's just a
book."
They they treat it like an encyclopedia
or something? Like they don't
they can't relate to those heavy-duty
instructions on a personal way. You see,
they they say, "Oh, that book's like way
beyond me, you know? I wouldn't use the
Bible to meditate. Give me just a little
something that somebody wrote later,
okay? And
a book where we say say, "In in this
hardcore meditator tradition, we go to
the classics. We go to the
we go to the explanations of meditations
which have survived 25 centuries of use,
okay? And like
Why It's like iTunes, you know? Just go
to the number one song.
And don't fool around with, you know,
number 83 or something, okay? Like
you have in front of you
a manual which has been used for for 2
and 1/2 thousand years. So, use it.
Okay? Got it?
Now, he gets kind of frustrated at this
point. Let's assume it.
Don't go for some
made-up thing that somebody thought of
last week,
that's going to disappear next next
week, okay?
Some advice big advice is from some
teacher or so-called great teacher
that's not going to
Nobody Oh, anyway.
They'll They'll boom means
These are like I don't know.
The equivalent in our world would be New
Age
something, you
anyway.
They'll boom means animals and they are
kind of little funky books. How's that?
Okay? Little funky books.
Seng ti
Seng ti means
somebody who didn't know what they were
talking about gave a teaching and
somebody wrote it down and they got it
wrong.
Yik chos means somebody dug under a rock
and found a little piece of paper with
some meditation thing written on it,
okay?
So, chos chos sheg la tsi cham po che pa
ni. But people
people go for the the dum lo books
because they're I guess cuz they're
little, I don't know. Dum lo told me,
"Don't publish how you We won't publish
how you work. You write a book about the
Yoga Sutra which is no longer than 100
pages." I said, "There's 200 verses. You
can't do it in 100 pages." He said,
"Yeah, but people want small books."
You see?
So,
anyway, he says, "Don't go for those."
Sheg la tsi cham po che pa ni. Yul son
ni tsal wa me tsal so we.
You are looking for what you want in a
place where it isn't and you are
refusing to look for what you want in
the place where it is. Got it?
Yeah? Make sense?
Okay.
Yul son ni tsal so we. It's like you
want a monster, you go to a bowling
alley, okay?
Okay. Ni tsal we. Nyen pa nyen me pa.
You're going to find it.
Je lam ni lam ni cham po shin ni kyi pa
ga tsi che du so pa ta yin.
Uh
You know, Jetsun Kapa talked about this
same problem in his greatest book ever
on the steps of the path to
enlightenment, he put a little What do
you call it? Ditty? What's a ditty?
A ditty's like a little limerick rhyme
thing.
And yeah, jingle. And Jetsun Kapa to
break the heaviness of his great
classic, he put some jingles in there.
And he said, "You know, you can read the
jingle that Jetsun Kapa put in his book
600 years ago
to explain this problem."
So, of course, I had to go find it for
you.
And I did.
And you have to listen to the whole
thing.
Yeah.
Yul gyal me pa. Here's my little ditty.
Do lo go lo ten gyu che mo le. Le sum
ting sum du pe yin ma ni. Du je ling we
lo du chin nam kyi. Je shin ma to rang
gi lo yin gyen.
Do lo go lo ten gyu che mo le. Le sum
ting sum du pe yin ma ni. The steps to
achieving incredibly deep meditation
which have been described so exquisitely
in the great classical commentaries and
even the Lord Buddha's own teachings.
Je je ling ling we lo du chin nam kyi.
The texts themselves, the style of
writing is too profound and too deep for
people. So, lo chin
lo du chin nam kyi. Those who lack
sufficient intelligence je shin ma to
rang gi lo yin gyen. If you can't figure
it out, that's your problem.
Okay?
Okay.
Sheg la go pe chos sum ge dam la. Ni tog
kyi we nam nam pa nyen me. Yul gyal shin
du ma tsal me ga tsal. Be ba du me tsal.
So shin nyen pa sen.
Uh
So, they decide that they should go
uh
Let me think.
They think it's impossible to find
anybody in the world who could teach
them how to how to read the classics on
meditation.
So, yul gyal shin du ma tsal. So, they
don't seek their meditation instruction
in the books that really have it,
they they seek it where you can't find
it. Got it? That's where the reference
comes from. So, make it sound. Be ba du
me tsal. They waste a lot of time and
they work really hard
in a
in a place where they're not going to
get anything, okay?
Nyam me.
So shin nyen pa sen.
The nature of all the number eight
things in dum gyal che pa nyen lo.
Gye pa tsal da ten gyu nyen pa lo je pe
dam pa du chin ba yin ten gyin.
Ting yin zin gyi kye pa kyi yin pa je
shin che pa gyur pa lo je gyur.
That's a long story.
They can't even distinguish between the
classical schools of ancient times,
okay?
Much less
distinguish between lower and higher.
The There are
There are average instructions for
meditation.
There are higher instructions for
meditation with which you can change the
world and fix the world. And there are
even higher
instructions on meditation where you
transform the world into a divine place,
okay?
They
They are hopeless when trying to dis
They don't even have those categories.
They just went for some little New Age
thing they heard at a yoga studio, okay?
Got it? All right.
Not that everything in a yoga studio is
bad, okay?
So, they go ni shin ni cham po yin ten
gyu tsal go le na kyi she.
So, I'm going to describe to you just
says Jetsun Kapa,
the way the teacher of the first Dalai
Lama,
how to
meditate properly from the classics and
if as it has been taught for 25
centuries.
But go lo yin na kyi she means, "But I'm
going to put it in
in terms that you can deal with. I'm not
going to like blow you away with some
technical stuff. I'm going to present it
in an easy way. And this poster is is
that.
I'm going to present it to you in a What
do you call it? Digestible way.
But um
it's going to be the hardcore stuff from
the classics
that was that has been used for 25
centuries, okay?
Na shin ni cham po she.
Sham lo che la.
Go lo jam pa yin. Do lo rang gi lo yin
che. Go ni shin ni chin du ma len pa.
Rang lo len chin nyen pa kyi ba tsal.
Uh
There are those of you in this audience
who have spent years
practicing
and studying the great teachings. Like
some of you have spent 15, 20 years
studying the great teachings.
Jam pa yin go lo rang gi lo yin che. And
you have in the your own possession
priceless jewels
of instruction on how to meditate
that have that have lasted for 2500
years.
Mhm.
Don't switch it for some cheap glass
ornament.
You see? He says, "Don't go buying
trinkets when you can get rubies. See
what I mean? Don't You have rubies. Grab
them and use them. And don't go running
after some What do you call it?
What do you call it? Costume jewelry
with
paste.
Costume jewelry. Costume Yeah. Don't go
for costume jewelry when you can get the
crown the royal jewels of England."
He said, "Geshe la, I have an extra day
in London after we did British Airways.
Him and Will?
Who Who was it?
Oh, Scott. Yeah, Scott and Calvin said,
"Geshe la, we have an extra day. British
Air kept us an extra day.
So, could What do you want us to do with
the extra day?" I said, "Go see the
Cullinan diamond.
It's the largest diamond in the world.
And it was broken up into the 11 largest
diamonds in the world. Got it? Like one
diamond was cut into 11. And they're
still the largest diamonds in the world.
I said, "Go see the Cullinan, you know,
go see the crown jewels of England in
the Tower of London, right?" So, I sent
them on this little trip,
you know. So,
if you don't go If you don't like
try to spend the time to grasp the deep
details of meditation that you're going
to learn
and and go to the Tower of London and
get these crown jewels, right? Don't go
What And then you're going to dump these
and go after costume jewelry? You know,
like that's what he's trying to say,
okay? You You
spend the time, make the effort. It's
hard.
It's not easy.
It's deep.
It's It's very subtle. There are lots of
incredible details.
But but those are the crown jewels. And
don't trade them in for some cheap
clothing you can get somewhere else, you
know? Don't don't trade them in for some
little
you know,
15-minute thing that somebody made up,
okay? All right.
It's hard and it's worth the effort.
It's like an Amelie taught by a good
teacher. All right.
You got the
goods, use them.
In the scriptures which you've already
studied,
there's nothing that God left out.
Didn't Buddha himself say,
"It's a lot more fun to be out in the
forest."
Think
about it. He's just saying it's more fun
to meditate than watch TV,
Work hard.
Learn all the details from the classics.
He says, "And my most important teaching
to you about meditation is find someone
who knows what they're talking about.
And and learn from them."
If you can't find a good teacher
and you bump up against the great
classics and they are too much for you,
relax.
And set them aside for a while, but
don't reject them, okay? Like set them
aside for a while. Say, "I I can't
handle that. I need someone to help me
with that."
And it's okay to shelf what do you call
shelf it for a while.
But don't don't reject it. Don't say,
"Oh, I'll never I'll never be able to go
through the real book on meditation."
In back of your
heart, in the back of your mind say,
"I'm going to crack that nut.
Sooner or later I'm going to
It may take me a while and I may have to
work hard,
but aren't the results so much better
when you work hard for something, right?
Than just someone hands you some little
costume jewelry and you you know,
you put it on, you know? It's It's more
fun to work hard and earn something
and get good at something.
And and in yoga also, right?
So he's saying,
"Tackle the Tackle the big ones.
The real classics on meditation. And
then then your meditation will be oh my
god. It'll be something beautiful,
okay?"
Okay, that's all right. Okay, here we
go.
So that was his
Diddy.
You can
If you just
uh take it easy
and go for some lightweight
little meditation thing that you heard
somewhere or you read somewhere,
uh you can
invest your entire life. You can invest
the rest of the years of your life
and you will just be spacing out and you
will never understand that that's not
meditation, okay? You will without the
proper instructions,
you will reach a state of meditation.
This is assuming you do it every day,
right? For years.
You will reach a kind of spaced-out
state, which is extremely dangerous. It
feels like meditation and it's not.
So if you don't get good instructions on
meditation,
you just take whatever somebody says
somewhere
and even those rare people who practice
it for years will be wasting their life
because it puts you into a very subtle
state of what do you call
You can call it spaced out.
You know what I'm talking about, right?
Spaced out.
And then
it actually ruins your mind. It hurts
your mind. I I I have these friends from
uh college.
You know, I gave up marijuana when I met
his holiness.
Me and my mom went to see his holiness,
you know, in India in I don't know, 1970
4 or 73.
In In those days you just knocked on his
door and you you know,
you just went in and we went in and we
sat down and
and he looks at me
and and he says uh
You know, that's the first thing he
says. He says, "Did you ever try drugs?"
Like I'm with my mom.
And uh
and I can't lie to the Dalai Lama.
So it was a non-problem. It was an
ethical quandary.
So I said, "Yeah, I tried it a little
bit." He said, "Tell me what it's like,
you know?"
And we talked about it for a while and
then he said, "Hey, you should just
learn to meditate. Then you don't have
to spend all that money,
you know?" And uh anyway, why did I
mention that?
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah. Yeah, I got
distracted.
So yeah, I have friends from those days
who didn't Oh, yeah, I stopped using
drugs from that day.
Uh I wasn't a big I used marijuana and
and maybe I took uh what do you call it
was mescaline. But anyway, twice. Okay,
twice.
But uh
so I stopped, but there are friends of
mine who kept going, you know? And
they're still smoking dope every day.
And their minds are just like mush, you
know? They have no motivation. They
They're constantly in financial trouble.
They They never quite get anything done.
Their whole house is covered with
half-finished things, you know? And and
it's sad. And their mind is just sort of
like
you know, toilet paper when you get it
wet?
I don't know.
It feels like that to me.
Uh you you try to have a conversation
with them and then somehow they lose the
point of They lose the sentence after a
few sentences and they and they look at
you and and then you're like, "Yeah?"
And then uh
If you meditate in a mistaken way and
you're one of those rare people who
actually keeps doing it
for years, your mind becomes like that,
okay? It's a big danger.
Your mind doesn't become more sharp,
more clear, more ethical, more pure,
more insightful. It just gets like mush,
okay? So
he says very very dangerous not to have
good instruction, okay?
There is a practice that was very
popular in India called Mahamudra and a
lot of you know it, okay?
It's also a yoga pose.
Uh
and this is a special kind of meditation
where the object that you take for the
meditation is your own thoughts, okay?
Your own mind. And rather than
visualizing a holy being or rather than
tackling a problem, a philosophical
problem, you focus on your own mind, on
your own thoughts,
And that's also dangerous that you can
get distracted by that. It is a very
good meditation and there are very high
versions of it, but it has a goal and it
and it has a a purpose.
And if you don't if you're not aware of
that, you can waste your whole life just
watching your mind, okay? So that's what
he's saying.
Uh some people have even described that
as the secret teachings, Samantabhadra.
This This is what tantra is. Some people
have misunderstood the meaning of tantra
and and they have spent their lives
watching themselves think about lunch.
Okay? Which is a useful practice if it
has a
a goal. You have to understand the goal
of that, okay?
I'm sorry.
They have fallen into a great error.
You can waste a thousand lifetimes that
way and accomplish nothing else of
meaning, okay?
Not just one lifetime. You can spend a
thousand lifetimes
with mistaken practices of meditation
and waste your time. Waste your life,
okay?
And I'm talking about the few people who
keep it up for their whole life, right?
Most people just give it up after a
couple weeks, okay? Here we go.
The fact that
there are many classical traditions of
Tibet. There are many Nyingma, Kagyu,
Sakya, Gelugpa, Bonpo. There are There
are many great
lineages of Tibet.
Um he says
uh there are people in each lineage,
including our own,
who have been called great.
But if you really
What do you call
If you examine them against the
teachings of their own school,
you can see that they have failed. You
see?
You compare them to what the teachings
of their own school say, and you can see
they didn't reach their goals. You see?
They They didn't follow their own
school's instructions. Okay?
Okay.
He's He's saying the instructions are
good in each tradition, but even these
people failed to follow them.
If you really check
The our tradition
uh
is not claiming that it's the only one,
and it's not claiming it's the best one.
He's just saying that the particular
tradition I'm teaching,
which comes down to Je Tsongkhapa.
Je Tsongkhapa had a thing. He
He started a lineage, the lineage of the
Dalai Lamas.
He started that lineage in which no BS
was was
put up with. You see? Because everything
that you learn in in a Dalai Lama
tradition monastery, you're required to
debate for 4 5 hours a day.
You're required to thrash it and discuss
it and
you're required to
to determine whether it's valid or not.
Everything we're taught every single day
for 25 years, we have to go for 3 4 5
hours and rip it apart and check if it's
true or not. You see? And
And that's just the What do you call
It's a ISO.
What's ISO?
There's a There's a ISO standard thing,
right? If you have a company, you can go
to the ISO in Switzerland or something.
And you can say, "You come to our
company
and you rate us. You rate our accounting
methods, etc. You rate our company's
honesty and what do you call integrity,
right?
And And if you're like have guts, you
invite these Swiss guys into your
company, and they spend like a couple
weeks there.
And they say, "Okay, your your
accounting is correct, and your methods
are are true, and the product you're
making is is is pure 100% what you say
it is." You see what I mean?
That's an ISO
rating. Then you get a ISO 1200 rating
or something like that. Um
The This lineage is like that.
Everything is checked and everything I
don't know how to say it.
Uh
There's an internal audit process
where if you try to say something which
doesn't make sense,
they write it down. They say, "Geshe
Michael said the following in a lecture
in Mesa on Saturday." They write it on a
piece of paper. They tie it to the tail
of a dog,
and then they chase it out of town.
That's the tradition, okay? Like you try
to insert some new stupid thing into the
tradition, and it's spit it out like an
antibody.
Okay? So anyway, you're you're in that
kind of
That's the where you ended up.
Okay? There's an internal audit process
where
started by Je Tsongkhapa where something
which was not
powerful and great was just spit out.
And it's just doesn't survive the test
of the daily debate, okay? Like that.
Okay.
Also, there's the fact that the guy who
started this Lamrim tradition,
his lama was who?
His main lama.
Maitreya.
Okay? His lama was an angel.
I mean a real divine being, you know?
Like he got to a point, which you can
read sometime, okay? It's beautiful
story.
But he he reached a point where he could
talk to
divine beings and ask them questions
when he wasn't sure of. Like you're
stuck with me.
Uh
He could just go to the top. You know?
He would say, "Uh Maitreya, I don't
understand this point." And then this
divine angel would appear
and explain it to you. Okay? It's very
beautiful.
So I guess, he says, maybe you and I
Maybe people like you and me He uses
Lamrim again, right? Maybe people like
you and me could maybe use this book,
maybe?
Okay? All right.
This is cute, okay?
This is a Pabongka idiom. He was kind of
funny
in a Tibetan way.
He said, "You can You But if you feel
like it, you can go try some You know,
people make up some little new
meditation.
And you can go study it with them, and
you can learn it, and you can work on
it.
And then you will probably get to some
new kind of enlightenment
that no one has yet has discovered, you
know? Like that. Okay, that's a joke.
Okay.
Whether you are studying the highest
levels of tantra, the highest levels of
secret practice, of which yoga is a
part, okay? Physical yoga is a part.
Whether you're studying that,
or whether you just want to be able to
concentrate better on fixing your car or
something, okay? Like from the highest
levels of secret practice down to fixing
your car.
If you want to
learn
a state of mental concentration or focus
which you can apply all the way from
fixing your car
up to the highest levels of secret
practice where you transform your very
body and mind into the divine,
he said,
"Learn the five problems.
Learn the eight antidotes, and you can
do it. Whether you want to fix cars,
whether you want better concentration so
you can recognize if the carburetor's
working right or not,
or whether you want to save the world by
becoming a divine being."
Somebody told me they saw the other day
What is it? The element
fifth element.
Yeah, if you want to become the
red-haired lady,
okay? Yeah, okay. Some people know.
Uh
or whether you just want to fix your
car,
if you want to have a mind which is
stronger and purer and more capable of
doing stuff, the opposite of the
pot-smoking person,
right? You want to be a person whose
mind is like a steel bear trap,
you know? And you can do anything.
And you can learn anything. You can
solve anything. Your mind is like
Because you need that kind of mind to be
really happy. You see? To really reach
happiness,
you need that kind of strong, pure,
clean, focused mind, okay?
If you want that, study the five
problems and study the eight fixes.
Okay? Study this poster.
Learn it.
And then your mind The level of your
mind will change, okay? It'll be really
beautiful.
It's kind of
interesting to think of your mind as a
piece of art, right? It's interesting to
think of your own mind
as a beautiful work of art. You see? You
You have an opportunity now in your
lifetime to repaint your own mind.
You know? You have an opportunity to
change
the beauty of your own mind into
something much more powerful, much
higher, much more pure, much more
inspired, you know? Much more able to
save
people in the world from suffering,
okay?
The people we took to British Airways,
right?
British Airways has 83,000 workers. They
have a $12 billion company. We took
these six people in, right? They were
trained in Dalai Lama.
And we took them into this big huge
company in UK.
And they got it. You know? We had like
25 of the top people in the room. And
they They saw these people's the state
of their mind, you know? And they were
so attracted, and they They just
Something happened. Something beautiful
happened, you know? These guys to show
from We didn't even have British
accents.
And
We didn't know how to say schedule.
And uh
I I wonder They sound weird to us, but
I'm wondering what We must sound to them
like, "Oh, what y'all doing here?"
And uh
So
But even though we were American, they
were like attracted to the people's
minds, and you could see it happening.
It's very beautiful. They were really
turned on by the people's ideas, you
know? I was afraid they were going to
steal some of them.
I'm always afraid of that. Okay.
They don't want me to mention anything
in the middle.
Do you want me to elaborate on that?
Okay.
You make up names.
You got to learn the five problems. You
got to learn the eight fixes for that.
If you don't, there's no way you're
going to be a great meditator.
Then I need a button ball. Okay, we're
on to the first problem. What time am I
supposed to stop this class?
6:00.
6:00?
Take a break.
Break, huh? Okay.
Yeah, I know.
Okay, here we go.
Then I I'll just go for a while. Okay.
All right. We have to finish a certain
amount every day or it'll be 20 years.
Okay.
The first
problem of meditation is what?
I don't want to meditate.
Just think of it as I don't feel like
meditating today. Because you and I know
that's your worst enemy already. You and
I know, those of you who have tried to
have a daily meditation practice, this
is what kills you.
This is what has always killed you. Get
over this one, the rest is easier, you
know?
It's like yoga, you know? Like I don't
feel like doing my yoga thing. Then
you're dead.
Then nothing will happen. Okay? So, it's
very important to discuss the antidote
for the first problem. Okay? How do you
get yourself to feel like doing yoga or
meditation today? How do you How do you
change? There are
half of the eight antidotes are
committed to problem number one. Got it?
That's why there's five and eight, okay?
There's five problems and eight
antidotes because the first one needs
four fixes.
Uh say depa.
damba.
sulwa.
shinjang.
These are the four. Very beautiful. Very
beautiful.
I always like to compare it to my high
school girlfriend, okay?
Which I can compare just about anything
to.
So,
in the pursuit of your high school
girlfriend, there are four steps.
All right?
Just I'm trying to think of an easy way
for you to remember. It could be a
boyfriend, okay?
Number one, depa. Depa means Depa in
Tibetan means faith, shraddha.
Shraddha in the India uh Shrimad
Bhagavatam is the grandson. It is
The real meaning of name is Shraddha.
Anyway,
it's a faith, okay? Faith. What does
faith mean
in these practices? It means
to admire the good qualities of
something.
So, first
the first time you meet the girl, I
remember I'm looking through the the
window in Mr. Bus's history class and
there's this girl, you know?
And and you see and you start making
lists in your mind about how cool they
are,
okay? That's
depa. That's shraddha. That's
You could call it admiration, maybe,
right? You make up lists in your head. I
like her hair. I like her eyes. I like
her nose. I like her chin. I And then
etc.
Okay? So, that's
that's depa.
If I learn to meditate,
oh man, you know? I can He's going to
make a list, okay? He's going to have an
admiration list for meditation.
That's step number one.
Think about all the cool stuff that's
going to happen to you if you meditate
well and that will get you on the
cushion.
If you truly believe you can lose weight
and look strong
and have a bright smiling complexion,
then you're going to get on the mat and
do your yoga, right? I mean, cuz you
think you're going to get something out
of it, right? Uh
so, there there's got to be reasons
to do it, right? So, that's the depa,
faith, okay? Shraddha.
Uh second one is damba. Damba means
after you look through the window of Mr.
Bus's history class
constantly and you make excuses to walk
by that room constantly
and you keep looking at all the cool
things you like about him or her, right?
What's going to happen next?
You're going to want
You're going to want her. See what I
mean? You're going to get hungry or what
do you call it?
Inspired.
You know, you're going to say, "I want
that." You know? Like I want her to be
my girlfriend.
That's it. Dumba means Dumba means you
you want it, okay? First you think about
how cool it is
and then you want it, right? So, dumba
means like I want to learn to meditate.
I want to do yoga. Wow, if all that
stuff can happen, I want to do it. Okay?
So, step two is very naturally flows
from step one. And you'll see that
later.
Step two naturally flows from number
one. When you think about how cool
something is, even if it's a car or a
house or
you know, anything, you're going to want
it, right? Dumba. Want.
Want it. Sulwa means Sulwa number three
means
then you'll be willing to what?
You'll be willing to put some effort
into it. You'll be willing to kick butt
to get it, right? If you consider how
cool it is
and if I considering how cool it is, you
really want it,
then you're going to be willing to do
some hard work, you know?
Jenny says to you, "Look, you can be a
You can get all these cool results from
yoga, but you're going to have to
You want to be a good yogi, but you're
going to have to work hard." And then if
you if you have in your mind all these
reasons why you want it,
then you'll be willing to put in some
work, okay? So, number three means the
hard work you're going to have to do
because you want it. Because you saw how
cool it was, okay?
So, no matter how many times she she
tells me she won't go out with me, I'm
going to keep trying.
Got it? I'm continuing the high school
girlfriend metaphor.
Okay. So, you know,
you're just persistent.
Even if it takes like 40 years, you just
persistent, okay? Okay, what's the last
one? Give us a
shinjang. Say shinjang.
Shinjang means you're going to get good
at
Shinjang means mental
and physically
good at meditating. Your body To people
who are talking to me today about all my
legs are falling asleep, forget it.
You know, you're going to reach a state
in your meditation where you're going to
be happy when it all falls asleep cuz
you've got to spend two or three more
hours.
You know, let it all fall asleep, you
know?
And then you're just like physically
you're like, "Wow." You sit down and you
go boom,
you know? You just body flows into that
posture and you're like boom.
Uh that's shinjang, okay? And then your
mind just returns on,
you know? You sit down, you get on your
cushion, you put your hands like that.
By the time that wrist hits the knees,
you're already there, you know? And then
you're like flowing.
And that's shinjang, mental and
physical. Physically you're you're like
in the saddle. I like to think I always
feel like, "Oh, I'm back in the saddle.
Ah."
You know, ah. If you do yoga a lot,
we Laura and Christina and I before
Surya Retreat, we asked the lady Ruth to
give us a class, Ruth Laura.
And
at the end of the class, we said, "Lady
Ruth, you know, we're going to have to
be helping each other, like adjusting
each other. Could you teach us some
adjustments?"
And she said, "Okay, uh
I'm going to get into this one where we
do asana and then you you do this
adjustment on me, you know?"
So, she got into it and then she said,
"Okay, do this with my shoulders." And
and we did it and she went, "Ah."
And then then she got into a handstand
or something and she said, "Okay, now
touch me here." And we touched her and
she went, "Mm."
You know? Because she's so doing yoga
all the time, she's done it so much
that
it just feels blissful. See what I mean?
Like anything we did, she would keep
going, "Ah. Mm. Mm."
And you know Lady Ruth, she's shy and
she's very quiet and and she couldn't
resist going, "Ah." You know? So,
shinjang means you hit the you hit the
mat, you hit the cushion. Shinjang is
like your your your wrist hits your
knee, your your finger
almost touches your thumb and then
you're in some zone already. That's
shinjang, okay? It It comes from what?
Hard work.
Why are you willing to do the hard work?
Cuz you want her.
Why do you want her?
Cuz you walked by that window 10,000
times and and saw You made lists in your
mind of all the cool stuff that was
going to happen once she became your
girlfriend.
And it does.
Okay? Got it?
Yeah. Uh
shinjang?
Uh just that word?
Uh depa, you can say d e p a,
which is uh
dumba d u m p a,
means I want it. I want her.
And then sulwa is t s u l w a,
which means I'm willing to put in the
work if it's necessary to get it. I'm
going to be persistent.
And then shinjang s h i n j a n g is
like that physical and mental What do
you call it? Zone. Like you're high. You
get high. You you you hit the zone and
you're like, "Whoa."
Okay? It'll come from the hard work.
All right.
So,
then I don't want to do anything to you
and do the martial arts. Mm.
You need to think things and do them in
your right number.
Things and so what's number?
So what is your version of challenge?
Number four is described as the result
of number three, right? Obviously.
You are able to get into the zone
because of
hard work. Hard work, daily practice,
hard work.
Uh come come to you need things and then
You're like number things and
Gombalajum ning ming the palm you.
The palm um shukani king to me new thing
lelo ne pa in thing.
Come come to you need things and then
The thing we are trying to reach is
called thing and then say thing and
then.
Thing and then.
Thing means the whole the object. Thing
means whole. Thing A say thing A.
Uh thing thing A means uh vivid. Okay,
like uh the color of spring trees or
spring grass, like a huge
meadow of spring grass. They've got they
call mo mo thing A mo thing A means
How do you say in English?
Vibrant.
Like it's like vibrating, vibrant color.
Thing thing and then the Tibetan word
for focus, meditation.
In in the Ashtanga what is it?
What are the last three the last three
anga?
Uh dharana
dhyana samadhi
Dharana
is thing, okay? Like focus.
The beginning. Thing and then it's like
focus.
Like deep and vibrant, okay?
So uh
the goal of meditation is to reach this
vibrant state of of attention, right?
I'm going to tell you now and I'm going
to keep saying it over and over again.
Good meditation feels like listening to
the most beautiful music you can imagine
and you're lost in it.
But you're not lost in it in a space
that way. Your mind is vibrant and and
and your mind is exploding, right? And
your mind is sharp and happy and
vibrant, right? You're deep deep into
some piece of music, right? Or you're
watching a movie and you're like
I took uh venerable Robina
we went out to see uh Braveheart. Oh,
that was a mistake.
You know, she's this little karate lady
monk nun from California, right? And and
she's a Braveheart. We're watching
Braveheart in the same
What's that town? The mall.
Santa Cruz, yeah. And she's like Punch
him! Kick him!
You know, and this is a Buddhist nun,
this little tiny Buddhist nun.
And we're theater and everybody's
staring at us, you know? But she is into
the movie.
You see like her mind is
She's She doesn't She thinks she's there
fighting with Braveheart, you know?
And
uh that's thing and then. That's thing
and then. Like good meditation is is
bright, happy, pure, engaged, excited,
turned on, you know, like in the zone,
you know? It's not this uh
Okay, got it? When you you the best book
you ever read and the best page of the
best book you ever read, how is your
mind at that moment? That's the state
you want to be in.
It's active, it's it's vital, it's
vibrant, it's happy, it's pure, it's
focused.
And it's like turned on, okay?
It's not like some kind of dullness.
That's a big danger,
Okay, then I'll tell you what thing is
and what we want is that.
Jum ning ming the palm ma shukani king
to me new thing
He defines the first problem, which is
lelo, not feeling like meditation is
Even you feel like not doing it at the
beginning. Those of you who know Tibetan
and you want to learn some new words
Jum ning ming ming ming da
means you don't have the heart. You
don't want the heart. Ning ming da,
okay?
Uh shukani or even if you do get into
the meditation uh
tu mi nu
you you're not able to sustain it, okay?
You get Even if you sit on the cushion
you can't sustain. You get up.
You just get up, you know? You just get
up after 5 minutes and you're thinking
about some email you didn't send or
something like that.
Ne pa in me de jong che ne money
The real He says the real antidote If
you had to pick one out of the four that
you thought was the opposite of that,
which one would it be? Last one. Yeah,
good.
Number four, okay? That
that like boom, that feeling of boom in
your body and you you get down on the
cushion
your your hands touch your knees and
you're there.
That's shinjang.
That's the real antidote to
lelo not feeling like meditating, okay?
If you If every time you ever sit down
you're going to have this boom
experience in the first 3 seconds
you're going to want to meditate cuz
it's it's cool.
It's cool to be in boom.
Okay, all right,
we did that. Ne ne ne pa in me de jong
che ne shinjang na deta
then tan da me cham de la pe thing and
then the unit sum bushin. We don't have
shinjang.
We don't have shinjang. We're not there
yet.
So what do you do?
Think about how cool it would be if you
had it.
I mean I'm sitting up here and I'm
describing some kind of thing that
happens to you. And in the back of your
mind you're you're saying I like that
movie. What? Harry Met Sally, right?
I'll then I'll stop. You can take a
break. If you got to listen to Harry Met
Sally.
I never saw that movie. Just people told
me about it.
And then I saw that one minute clip of
that part. But there's I don't I don't
know what the movie's about even.
But apparently some lady is having
dinner with some man.
And then she's having an orgasm during
the dinner. So she's They're eating like
hamburgers or something in this nice not
in a steak probably. They're in a big
nice restaurant. And she's They're
talking and she's going
you know? And then uh this this
well-dressed lady comes in like a white
suit, like she's like 60 and she's got
the nails and the What do you call it?
Pearls and stuff and her hair is up. And
and then she comes in and sits down. And
then the waiter is all dressed up in
white. What do you call it? A white
jacket? Dinner jacket? And he comes over
and he hands her a menu.
You know, I didn't see it, okay? So I'm
just
He hands her a menu.
And and she doesn't take the menu cuz
she's looking at this lady going uh uh
uh.
And then the the waiter says, "Madam,
you know?" And she's like, "Yes."
And and he says, "What What would you
like to have for dinner, you know?" And
she says,
"Give me whatever she's having."
So even if you don't have shinjang
you can
you can say to yourself I want I I don't
know what it's like. I've never I
haven't had shinjang, but I'm getting a
smell from this guy. There must be
That sounds pretty cool. I would like
Give me what they're having.
Give me what they're having. That's
depa.
Depa means
That sounds cool.
So I'll tell you how the shinjang to
overcome your laziness
use your faith.
Uh
Use your Use what you've heard about how
cool it is to substitute for the
shinjang for a while, got it?
I I want to meditate. Why? I think I'll
have what he's having.
You know, got it?
Okay.
And then I'll tell you to me.
Uh
I think we should take a break.
So
uh
we'll take a 10-minute break.